This is the Enigma,
the encryption machine
used by the Nazis in World War two.
I see that there is a sigil
from the Nazi Party on this one,
so it must be the real thing.
Yes. This was actually used
by the Germans in World War II.
Someone actually asked me the other
day, did Hitler use this machine?
And I said, I don't know,
but
Benedict Cumberbatch and
Keira Knightley did.
Woah, no way!
Could we try encrypting a word?
Yeah.
- I have just a word for us.
You'd never guess what it is.
- So that's our plaintext.
That is our plaintext.
So we need to press the keys.
And look at the lamps
that light up,
which will give us our ciphertext.
So the first one is V.
We have a J.
Okay. Then an E.
- F
- Then an R.
We have an M.
That is an L.
Now for
someone to decrypt this message
they need to type this text
into another Enigma machine.
But not just any enigma.
Their machine has to be set up
in the exact same way as the one
that encrypted the message.
So we need to turn these rotors
back to the initial setting.
That means adjusting
a series of rotors and wires
to exactly one of trillions
of possible combinations.
If you get it right....
Finally, the L gives us:
- Veritasium
It worked. Yeah.
The message appears,
but if just a single setting
is out of place, well, then
the encryption remains unbroken.
I can see how decrypting
such a thing
would get very complicated
very quickly.
This is exactly what the Nazis
relied on.
Hitler
had come into power in Germany
and the Nazi Party had taken over.
Today we rule Germany.
Tomorrow the world.
By 1939, they were sending hundreds
of encrypted messages
across Europe every day.
With the allies desperately trying
to guess the Enigma settings.
But even if they sometimes
got lucky and cracked a message
each day at midnight,
the Germans would change
the settings
on all their Enigma machines,
so none of it would help them read
the next day's messages.
That's why British intelligence assembled a team of the country's greatest minds:
chess players,
crossword fanatics and university
academics including Alan Turing,
along with hundreds of women
from the Royal Navy.
And bit by bit,
they looked for flaws
hidden deep within the machine.
But they also searched for subtle
mistakes made by German operators.
At its peak, around 9000
men and women
were executing the most secret code
breaking operations in the world.
Out of an unsuspecting mansion
in the English countryside.
This is a video
about the incredible methods
and machines that broke the enigma.
Let's start
with how the Enigma actually works.
And I think the first thing
you need to know about the Enigma
is that it wasn't actually invented
by the Nazis.
It was patented in 1918
by a guy called Arthur Scherbius.
He was a German inventor
who wanted to encrypt messages
for banks and businesses.
Were Enigma machines
readily available?
Could you, like,
buy one in Germany,
or were they kept a secret anyways?
This, by the way, is Sir
Dermot Turing.
He's Alan Turing's nephew.
The company that was making Enigma
machines was really trying
to find a market for them,
so you could definitely go out
and buy them.
And lots of countries did.
So Poland bought one,
the British bought one,
the Russians bought one,
you name it.
And there's one thing in particular
that made Enigma superior
to other encryption methods.
And you only need to play around
with it
for a bit to figure that out.
I'm going to press the L key.
And when I do that,
you'll see that one of the lamps
on the lamp board lights up.
The Y.
That means
that the plaintext letter L
has been encrypted as a Y.
If I press the L again,
what do you think might light up?
Maybe the Y again?
- Maybe the Y.
So let's press it again
and see what happens.
And what has lit up there.
Well that's an H not a Y.
So it's not a Y. So it's changed.
Okay, so with every key press
the substitution is different.
- Yes.
This is what separates the enigma
from the most famous encryption
methods
that came before, the Caesar cipher
or simple substitution ciphers.
These all encrypt
according to a fixed rule.
Enigma changes that rule
with every single letter you type.
And for the reason for that,
we need to open the box
even further
and see what's happening inside.
Yeah, that'd be great.
Okay, so I'm going to open this up.
Inside the Enigma there are three
rotors.
Each rotor has 26 metal contacts
on either side, one
for each letter of the alphabet.
So when you slot them
into the machine,
current flows
from one rotor to the next,
the wiring between
the contacts is totally scrambled.
So for example, when you type
a Y current flows down the
Y wire to the first rotor,
where it first gets switched to an
H, and then in the second rotor,
the H gets swapped to a B,
and in the third rotor
the B gets swapped to a q.
Then a component called
the reflector directs
the current back through the rotors
by a completely different path,
ending up as a letter E.
The current
then goes up to the lamps
above the keyboard and illuminates
the letter
E, indicating how the
Y has been enciphered.
I just want to say a big
thanks to Jared Owen,
who made the 3D model of the Enigma
for his YouTube
channel and has kindly
let us use it here.
So check out the link in the
description for his original video.
Now, the moment you type
a letter into the Enigma,
the rotor on the right rotates.
And that's how a rotor encryption
machine works,
that it actually moves the rotor
when you press the keys.
So if you type
the same letter again,
it will follow
a completely different path
through the machine,
which means you'll get
a different letter
each time you press the key.
So here you can
see the rotors in position. Yes.
And when I press the key
you can at the back
see levers
which push up against the rotors.
Could you press the button? Oh, I see.
There we go.
There's actually three levers.
And they are set to the right hand
side of each rotor.
So there's one for each rotor
trying to push the three rotors
around.
But it's only the first rotor that
turns every time you press a key.
Right. Yeah.
The second rotor will only turn
when the first rotor
reaches a certain position.
There's a notch
that's connected to the ring.
That notch will allow the lever
at the back to drop.
And then connect with the ratchet
on the next rotor along.
So this rotor turns until the notch
comes into the turnover position.
When it does
so that allows the second lever
to drop in and engage with
the ratchet on the second rotor,
which will then
allow the second rotor to turn.
You'll see as the rotors turn
the second
rotor turned at the same time.
So after
26 rotations of the first rotor,
the second one turns once.
- Yes.
And then after 26 rotations
of the second rotor,
the third one
turns once?
- Yes. Absolutely.
Yes. So the third one turns
very very rarely.
Yes. Okay.
The operator can slot
the three rotors
into the machine in any order.
That's three times two times one
equals six possible permutations.
Then there's the starting position
of each rotor,
which is shown in the window
before the operator starts typing.
This is called the window setting.
There are 26 numbers on each rotor,
so that's 26 cubed possibilities.
Multiply that by six possible
rotor orders.
And that's over
100,000 ways to set up
this commercial Enigma machine.
But what the Germans did was
they not only bought them,
but they said we're going to modify
them.
We're going to modify them in a way
that nobody else knows
what we've done.
There were a few ways
that they did this.
So if I undo this clasp here,
I can actually turn the ring round.
And that changes the relationship
between the letter that appears
at the top
and the fixed wiring of the rotor.
I see.
So rotating the ring
does two things.
First, it offsets
the letters from the rotors
internal wiring for example
at first
this rotor connects 1 to 4.
So it changes A to D.
But rotate the ring by one.
And that same wire
now connects 2 to 5.
So it changes B to E instead.
And second it changes the position
where turnover occurs on
the adjacent ring.
But there was another vastly
more complex upgrade.
There is another part
of the machine
that we haven't looked at yet,
and this was a part
of the machine that was added
by the German military.
It's called the plug board.
Each of the keys is connected
by a wire to the plug board.
So the plug board
has a letter for each of the keys,
because it means that you can
substitute the letter,
say the first one we have here,
which is Q and that's plugged
into R.
The Q coming from the keyboard
will go into the entry wheel
into the first rotor as an R,
but if there's nothing plugged in
it will carry straight through.
Now let's consider how this impacts
the number of ways
messages can be encrypted.
This is also known as the key
space.
The revolvable rings
change the position
where the second
two rings would turn over.
So that's 26 squared possibilities.
And then on the plug board,
if you swapped just one
pair of letters, that would
introduce 325 more possibilities.
But in the late
1930s, the Nazis typically swapped
around six letters.
And that's 100 billion
possibilities.
Overall that brings the grand total
for the key space to over
seven times ten to the power of 18.
But as long as the machine
is set up exactly how it was
at the start of the encryption,
you can type in the ciphertext
and get out
the original message intact.
This is also called the plain text.
If both machines are in the correct
settings and I press an E,
it will encode to a k going through
the complicated set of wires.
But if I press the K under the same
settings, it'll go back to an E.
So it's like a closed loop of
electricity.
So we have a k.
Oh, it seems to be working! E.
The way the Germans ensured
that all enigmas on a particular
network were set up in
the same way was by sending out
prearranged instructions
for each day of the month.
These were called the key sheets.
So each morning
when the operator
sent their first message,
they would reconfigure
their machine
to the new daily settings,
and that would allow them to
encrypt and decrypt messages
to other Enigma operators.
But what if you didn't
have the key sheets?
Well, then you would have
to figure it out from scratch.
By the end of the 1930s
this problem had become urgent.
As Nazi Germany grew more powerful,
British intelligence could sense
that war was becoming
increasingly likely, and they knew
that Enigma messages could reveal
what German forces were planning,
but only if the messages
could be deciphered in time.
So British intelligence
assembled a secret workforce
focused on doing just that.
We're at Bletchley Park.
This was Britain's most important
codebreaking operation
during World War Two.
Bletchley was an unremarkable town,
but it was situated conveniently
between London and the country's
two most prestigious universities,
Oxford and Cambridge,
which is where the
British intelligence
sought their new recruits.
And alongside
these academics, Bletchley Park
also recruited women from the Royal
Navy known as Wrens,
and the whole operation
was kept as secret as possible.
To give you an idea of the secrecy,
here is something
that the code breakers at Bletchley
Park had to follow.
Some of the rules: do not talk at
meals or in transport or traveling.
Do not talk by your own fireside.
Be careful even in your own hut.
All in all, seems like a very
secretive place to work.
Together this group of around 150 people
started trying to break the enigma.
And here was their plan.
First listening stations
would intercept German
radio messages
and send them to Bletchley Park.
Second, codebreakers
would analyze the day's traffic,
looking for patterns and weaknesses
in the encryption.
And third,
they would use those clues
to try and guess the settings,
and then they would
put those settings
into their own enigmas,
finally cracking the messages.
But all this rested on
one key component
the British needed a working
version of the Nazi Enigma machine
to figure out the settings,
but they didn't have one.
See, on top of adding
revolving rings and the plug board.
The Nazis had made another upgrade.
They had also changed the wiring
inside each rotor.
That meant the Nazi rotors
scrambled the letters
in a completely different way
from the commercial Enigma,
and without knowing
the wiring of the Nazi rotors,
it was impossible
to determine the settings
the Nazis were using each day.
So the codebreakers were stuck.
So it was completely hopeless.
And that was the situation
at the beginning of July 1939.
They really hadn't
made any progress at all.
But what the British
and the Germans didn't know
was that years earlier,
another country
had already launched
a secret effort to break Enigma.
In 1931,
an employee at the German Armies
cipher office made contact
with French intelligence, offering
to sell secrets about the Enigma
in exchange for a handsome fee.
He handed over
operating procedures,
sample messages,
and even key sheets.
Now, the French
didn't know what to do with them,
so they shared them
with their Polish allies,
and the Polish gave the sheets
to their codebreaking
team of mathematicians,
who spotted a vulnerability.
After an officer set up his enigma
for the day.
He had to choose three
random letters before
sending a message, for example GEX.
Then he would transmit these three
letters, encrypted on the day's
default settings,
and he'd do it twice,
just in case of a bad signal.
For example, the encrypted letters
would come out as ASDEIW.
After that, he would move
his rotors such that these same
three letters GEX
would appear in his window up here.
These were the so-called window
settings.
And finally he would be able to
type out the rest of the message.
Now the receiver would decipher
the first six
letters of the message,
and they would get GEX GEX
and they would know that they had
to change their window settings
to GEX at this point, and only then
would they be able to decipher
the rest of the message.
So it was encrypted twice.
- Right.
Which was a security flaw,
because if you encrypt something
twice,
you have a relationship created
by the first letter of the key
that's been chosen.
And the fourth letter,
the same letter has been encrypted
because you're sending it twice.
Okay. Just the three second letter
and the fifth letter as well.
Okay I see.
And they had this brilliant guy
called Marian Rejewski
who essentially said, oh,
I recognize this is a problem
in permutation theory
from when I was doing
my undergraduate mathematics.
This meant that by 1933,
the Poles had reconstructed
the wiring
of the military version of Enigma,
even though they'd never seen one,
they never captured one.
And so that meant
they were able to reverse engineer
and make replica Enigma machines,
and then they could
start working out
what the settings problem was
and how to how to solve that.
So by the mid 1930s,
the Poles were actually able
to read German military
Enigma traffic.
But in 1939 the Nazis
were getting ready to invade.
So they upped their security again
by first making two extra rotors.
So now it was five to choose from,
not three.
And that's five times
four times three.
So 60 possible orders
that increased the key space
by a factor of ten.
And on top of that
they switched from using six
plug board swaps to ten.
That's around 150 trillion
combinations from the plug
board alone.
So all in all, the key space
had grown by a factor of 15,000
to over 100 sextillion.
The Polish needed help,
and by July 1939,
they knew a German
invasion was likely.
So the Poles called
an urgent meeting
with British
and French intelligence.
They revealed everything they knew
about
the Enigma machine itself,
the wiring, and they revealed
everything they knew about
the daily setup of the machine.
Just over a month
later, Poland was invaded.
Their codebreakers fled and
they had to leave behind the device
they'd invented to break into
Enigma messages called The Bomba.
The Brits were now on their own.
They were armed with the knowledge
given to them by the poles,
but now it was up
to them to break the enigma.
Our producer
has crafted an Enigma message,
and I'm going to try and use
all of the tips and tricks
that the British knew about
to try and crack this thing,
see if I can get it right.
FAO Gregor.
Urgent decryption required.
We're on it.
Okay, so the first thing to look at
is the top of the message.
By the 1940s, the Germans quickly
realized that encrypting
three letters
twice at the start of each message
was a terrible security flaw.
So they came up with a new system.
After setting up the Enigma,
the operator would now start each
message with three random letters,
for example VER,
and they would send them
completely unencrypted,
naked over the air,
and then they would set
their own window
settings to those three letters.
So VER.
With that the operator would pick
another three random letters,
say ITA.
But this time they would type them
through the Enigma.
These three letters were called
the indicator, and after this
they would set their own window
settings to the indicator
so it reads ITA before
finally typing
through their actual message.
Likewise,
when a receiver got the message,
they would know that
the first three letters
VER came through unencrypted
and they would put them
into their window settings
and type out the next three letters
in the message.
They would get three
decrypted letters out, ITA,
and they would put those
into their window settings next.
And now they were finally ready
to read the rest of the message.
So a receiver is only able to
decrypt the message
if they could follow these
two randomized checkpoints
at the start of each message,
which should have been
a great security addition,
except people are terrible
at being random.
People
very rarely choose random letters.
So, for instance,
the German operator's
girlfriend's name was one
that was chosen quite a lot.
So for instance,
one common one is Cilla.
Okay.
- Which would be CIL.
CIL.
- Hence the term cillies.
And it wasn't just girlfriends
names either.
So if the window setting you
send in plaintext is BER,
like you might be like, well,
I wonder if they just chose
Berlin.
And so you would deduce,
you just say
I guess the indicator
is probably LIN.
Okay.
So my message starts with Lon.
So I'm guessing that the operator
just chose London.
So I know that CNG were encrypted
from DON.
Okay, so here's a universal
simulator for the Enigma.
And I can actually show you
that if I put in the window
settings on the rotors.
LON, I know that if I type CNG,
I'm supposed to get out DON
for London, but for this to work,
I need to guess the correct rotor
order out of all of the rotors,
and I need to get the correct
ring settings and the plug board.
So there's still a lot of guesswork
to do
for me
to be able to get this right.
Okay, so I'm now going to record
some me actually trying this
DON no, DON no.
I'm, I'm struggling a bit.
I won't lie, I am struggling a bit.
But there was another way
the laziness of the operators
came through.
It was spotted by a British
codebreaker, John Herivel.
He compared the messages
from all over the network
that came
from many different operators, and
he noticed something interesting.
Those three letters
the operators started their
messages with appeared random,
but they all seemed to be
a very similar random.
If you looked at just the first
letter every operator chose across
hundreds of messages.
They weren't spread
evenly across the alphabet.
They centered around
a specific location.
Same for the second letter
and same for the third.
This happened
because the operating procedure
required the operators to shuffle
the rotors from the default
key sheet settings for the day,
those ring settings.
And as it turned out,
a significant number of operators
only shuffled their rotors
by a position or two.
It's sort of
like how people lock their bikes
and only move the rotors
a small amount.
Following the same logic,
Harrisville concluded
that the clustering of window
settings around
a particular set of three letters
throughout the day
actually revealed
what the daily ring settings were,
so this became known
as the Herivel tip.
So I know that the Herivel tip or the ring
settings are MON,
so I can convert them into,
well, what
that letter is in the alphabet.
So M is the 13th, 15th is O,
and then 14th is N.
I don't know this by heart,
I googled it.
Now I know that if I type DON,
I'm supposed to be getting CNG out.
So now I've got to guess
the rotor order for what rotors
they were using today.
And there were some hints,
but besides that, it was basically
just a lot of brute force.
You just had to try them.
Let's try one, two three. Don.
No, no, not even close.
132 15 and 14
ZNG. Oh there we go.
ZNG sounds pretty close to CNG
that we're supposed to get.
I think I've guessed the rotor
order to be one, three and two.
All that remains
now is the plug board.
So maybe a Z needs to become a C
a Z and a C.
DON.
CNG!
There we go.
So if I was to change my window
settings now to Don, that's
that second step of randomization.
...THPKAKTQOG...
okay this kind of looks like text.
Looks like James.
A D and an E.
Haha, okay!
Oh that took a while.
There was a lot of plug board
guesses,
but I think
I finally figured it out.
It says James is a legend.
James the producer.
Okay, we got it. There
we go. It took.
How long did it take me?
Pencils down, everyone.
One hour straight.
That's tough.
But that was actually an easy
example.
Bletchley codebreakers
would have been faced
with figuring out
multiple plug board swaps,
and in a single message,
it would be highly unlikely to use
both the Herivel
tip and the cillies,
even with the operator errors
to help them, codebreakers
at Bletchley had to trawl
through hundreds of messages
each day
just to get a clue of what
the Enigma settings were.
And doing
this manually was a huge task.
To make it even harder,
some networks were much more secure
and didn't
have any of these human errors,
making them far tougher to crack.
So what Bletchley Park needed
was an automated way to break these
Enigma messages,
and that came from exploiting flaws
in the machine itself.
You see, the weakest part
of any encryption device
is not the device itself.
It's the human that's operating it.
And kind of like the Enigma.
Human error
is also one of the biggest reasons
why our information leaks
onto the internet.
You can make an account
on the wrong website,
or you give your phone number
to the wrong company,
and your data can end up in the
hands of a data broker,
who can then sell it on to scammers
who can impersonate you online or
target you with AI powered scams.
But you can protect yourself
against this
with the help of today's sponsor,
Incogni.
Incogni contacts
data brokers on your behalf,
and then they request
that those data brokers
delete your information.
I've been using Incogni
since June 2025,
and they've completed
143 requests on my behalf.
And also it runs in the background.
I don't need to do anything,
so it constantly requests
these removals.
On their unlimited plan
you also get your own personalized
risk assessment each month,
which means you get practical steps
on how you can improve your
online privacy.
They also have an exposure scanner,
which finds
wherever your personal info
shows up online,
and they put it all in one place
so that you can
then choose
what you want to take down
with the help of Incognis
human removal specialists.
To get your data off the market
today, you can go to
Incogni.com/Veritasium and use
the code Veritasium
to get 60% off their annual plan.
You can also click the link in the
description or scan this QR code.
So I want to thank incognito for
sponsoring this part of the video.
And now back
to breaking the Enigma.
So Bletchley Park
needed to develop a way
to automate the breaking of Enigma.
And luckily for them,
there was one man in particular
who was uniquely qualified
for the job.
Alan Turing had already gained fame
for his paper
on a device that since became known
as a Turing machine,
so the British were quick
to recruit him at Bletchley Park.
When Turing arrived,
he realized that if he could
describe the process of breaking
the Enigma as a sequence of some
logical tests, then he could
theoretically devise a machine
that would do the job for him.
So we're in hut eight,
and this room is the one
that apparently Alan Turing
used as his office when he was
put in charge of the naval
Enigma problem.
They've changed a tin
tea mug to the radiator,
which Alan Turing allegedly did.
I think what happened was that
people would take his mug away
to wash it up, and then he couldn't
find it when he wanted it.
Can you tell me more about, like,
what kind of a person he was?
Really quite wicked sense of humor.
Very irreverent
and very interesting as well to
to talk to if you were interested
in the right kind of thing.
So if you want to talk to him about
a football game, then frankly,
think again.
But if you want to talk to him
about the possibility
to build a machine
that might be able to play
a game of chess,
he’d have lots to say about that.
To automatically break
the enigma, Turing
needed a logical test
that a machine could perform
some series of procedures,
after which the machine would say,
oh no, these are not the Enigma
settings. They're wrong.
You should try something else.
Or yes, these could be the correct
Enigma settings.
Now you should try and decipher
the message with them.
The test that he ended up
devising came
from the fundamental flaw
in the Enigma, and surprisingly, it
exploited some of the most
unimportant and mundane messages
that the Nazis were sending.
Certain German outposts
sent very similar messages
at the same time every day,
and that would be a weather report.
So, for example, if Bletchley Park
intercepted a message
every day at 6 a.m.
from an operator in Biscay,
the code breaker might reasonably
guess that somewhere inside
this message, there would be text
that says weather report Biscay,
or in German, WETTERVORGERSAGEBISKAYA.
And there was a way to guess
where that text was encrypted
in the message.
If I'm pressing an L,
I can keep pressing the L on here,
and the L on the lamp
panel will never light up.
You can't encrypt a key
to become itself.
No. Because the current can't
flow back through the same wire,
it has to go
through a different wire.
That means I can take this word
and I can shift it over the
enciphered text
until I find a position
where no letter is
enciphered as itself.
So if I start, for example,
with W and Q aligned
so that the two messages
align at the start
and I scanned through here,
this S is enciphered as itself.
So that isn't a possible solution.
So I'm going to shift it
one letter down and try again.
Now I have a V enciphered as a V
and an E enciphered as an E.
So this doesn't work.
So I'm going to shift
another position.
Oh no I have an R enciphered
as an R.
So that doesn't work either
I'm going to shift it
one more.
That all looks good.
So here we go. Bingo.
Now there's no letter
that is enciphered as itself.
So my guess
is that this part of the enciphered
text says weather report Biscay.
And this guess at what the
enciphered text actually represents
is called a crib.
At Bletchley Park in hut eight they had
what was called the cribbing room.
This is Jonah Weinbaum.
He wrote his thesis on
how the enigma was broken.
And the cribbing room, their job was to identify
good, strong,
consistent cribs,
which consisted of either
weather messages, patterns
they had noticed across messages.
The usage of slang
or shorthand.
After Turing
was sure that he had a crib
that reasonably guessed
what the encrypted message
stood for
he started with his logical test.
He assumed that
at the start of each message,
the window settings for the Enigma
were ZZZ or 26, 26, 26,
and that the second rotor hadn't
turned in this part of the message.
So as soon as the first letter
is typed,
the rightmost rotor turns to A
or 1. At that position
typing
a W in the machine outputs an R,
and that means that
with the Enigma machine
in this particular state, W
is wired to R, and R is wired to W.
As each letter is typed,
the rightmost rotor moves
one step forward,
so when the window on the right
reads two,
E and W are wired together,
at three, it's T and I, and so on.
Now Turing notice that this
encryption produced a kind of loop.
For example, at position six,
the Enigma machine maps R to Y,
but at 22 it maps Y to S,
and at nine it maps R to S.
So Turing
imagined taking a clone
of the Enigma machine
at each of these positions.
Then the only difference between
these machines is just the position
of that rightmost rotor.
It's either 6, 9, or 22.
Now look what happens if you wire
these three machines back to back,
so that the output of Enigma
6 becomes the input of Enigma 22,
and then the output of 22 becomes
the input of nine.
If Turing hit the letter
R on the first machine,
it would output a Y.
Then the second machine
would then transform that
Y into an S,
and the third machine would take
that S back to an R,
creating a perfect loop.
R turns back into R.
Now for this to happen,
the settings on these three
Enigma machines have to match
the settings
used to encrypt
the original message,
but if the settings don't match,
for example,
if the rotors used in
the enigmas are different,
then the test is extremely unlikely
to produce a loop and R
should turn into a different letter
instead.
This gave Turing the logical test
he was after.
Theoretically,
he could create a machine
that looks through all possible
Enigma settings, such that
when you offset the first rotor
by 6, 22, and 9 an R
is transformed back into itself.
Now, out of millions of possible
settings,
there are multiple combinations
that can transform
an R back into itself
at positions 6, 22, and 9.
Turing's test could return
hundreds of false positives, so
he needed more logical constraints,
which came in the form
of more loops from that crib
we saw earlier.
Back in the message
notice that R maps to W
at position 1 and then W to E
right after that,
and then goes E to O at position
8, O to S, and then back to R,
which completes the loop.
Following this process,
Turing built up an entire menu of
these loops of logical constraints.
But this whole test
rests on the assumption
that we've guessed the right
rotor order.
Remember that the Germans
had five rotors to choose from,
and they could slot
any three of them into the machine
in any order.
That's 60 possible configurations.
So Turing's
machines had to run through
this entire process again and again
for each rotor order.
And that still left one component
unaccounted for, the plug board
and the 150 trillion
possible ways to hook it up.
But even though this number
is ridiculously large, Turing
found a simple way to isolate
the plug board's effects.
Remember how a letter flows
through the Enigma?
First through the plug board,
then through the rotors,
then back out
via the plug board again
so we can break each enigma
into three steps.
If you type an R into the Enigma,
it first gets transformed
by the plug board
to, for example, a Z
and then that gets transformed
by the rotors to a Q.
Now this Q again gets transformed
by the plug board to an X.
So X is the letter
that flows into the second enigma.
But the plug board on the second
enigma is set up in the same way.
So it swaps that X back to a Q.
So Q goes to X goes to Q.
In other words, back to back
plug boards cancel each other out.
So we can actually simplify
this long list of transformations
to this.
That means Turing could treat
any series of Enigma machines
as the plug board on the way in.
Then the combined effect
of all the rotors
and then the plug board
on the way out.
But remember, with the correct
settings, these three
Enigma machines
transformed an R back into an R,
which means if the first plug board
transformed an R to a
Z on the way
in, then the last plug board
must have transformed a Z into an R
on the way out.
So the three rotors alone
must also create a loop,
transforming that same letter
Z back into itself
with no plug board needed at all.
Much like the original loop
through the three enigmas,
Turing realized
this formed the basis of a test,
one that he could perform
using a simple electrical circuit.
He'd start with a guess,
say that R is plugged to Z,
and set that wire live.
If the guess was correct,
the three enigmas would transform
that Z back to itself, leaving
a single loop of live wires.
If the guest was wrong,
it's likely that Z would loop back
to a different letter,
and that letter would loop round
to another and another.
So current
would keep looping around
and around the circuit,
setting multiple wires live.
But that would mean
that R was simultaneously plugged
into multiple letters,
which is impossible.
This contradiction allowed him
to rule out all these letters
as a candidate
for what R is connected
to on the plug board,
and if all 26 wires went live,
he knew that there was no possible
plug board
configurations
for that window setting,
so his machine would move
the rotors
one step forward
and start the test again.
There were also cases
where 25 wires could light
up, leaving just one dark.
Since those 25 possibilities
had all been ruled out,
that wire that didn't light up
pointed
to the only remaining candidate for
are to be connected to on the plug
board.
This was Turing's stroke of genius,
even though there were 150 trillion
ways to configure the blackboard.
Starting with this, one
guess would allow his machine
to rule out multiple possibilities
or even reject incorrect
settings entirely.
The guests didn't even have to
be correct for this to work.
They did do this by hand.
They did these contradictions,
you know, on a piece of paper,
following through what is implied.
But Turing designed this machine
so that it was instantaneous,
like it was at the speed,
not the speed of light.
But the speed of electricity
flowing in a wire.
With the help of an engineer,
Harold Keen, Turing
brought his device to life.
Based on some of the ideas that they got
from the Polish Cipher Bureau
just before the war
started, Turing and his colleagues
came up with this.
He called it The Bomb, named in
honor of the Polish
Bomba, the device that the Polish
mathematicians invented to break
the earlier versions of Enigma.
First prototype,
arrived in March of 1940,
which in itself is a pretty startling achievement,
given the war only started
in September 1939.
Yeah.
To get the civil service,
to not only approve his design
and then to get the finance
to be able to build the thing.
Absolutely astonishing.
Anyway, this is essentially 36
Enigma machines
working in parallel,
working backwards.
So you start with an assumption
that you've made that
a certain piece of ciphertext
represents certain plaintext meaning.
Give all that to the machine,
let the machine go to work.
And at the end of the process,
the idea is you're going to derive
the key of the day
that the original Enigma operator
was using
to encipher that message,
which means now you can read
every message that that guy sent,
not just
the one that you're analyzing.
And so when we run the machine,
we're hoping for a condition
when every enigma will find
the answer
it's been told to find all
at the same exact instant.
And when that happens, you've
essentially solve this equation
and the machine will stop
and give you an answer.
So what I'm going to do now is I'm
going to run the machine.
- Okay
Let’s do it.
It's going to be quite loud.
Eventually you're going to get
through all the combinations
26 times 26 times 26
17,500 or so.
Yeah,
it's going to take the machine
about 13 minutes
to go through all of those.
Right?
And at some point,
we're hoping that the machine is
going to find an answer that works.
At which point
it's going to come to a stop
assuming the machine is actually
working correctly.
What are the chances that it is
working correctly?
About 90%.
Okay, to be fair, that's good.
It's better than my brain.
-And mine.
Okay, so what's going to happen?
Machines found a solution.
Okay, there we go.
And if you look at these drums
on the right hand end, that's
where the solutions are indicated.
These are called
the indicator drums.
It's the output from the machine.
And if you look very closely
you'll see a little pointer
on each of those drums
pointing to the letters D, K and X.
So that's the machine saying
I think DKX is an answer.
Now I'm saying an answer,
not the answer.
The problem is that you might
get multiple answers, because it's
quite possible you'll find
several solutions to the equation.
And there is a flaw hiding
in Turing's original test.
Sometimes the machine would stop on
what looked like a clean, valid
loop, but in reality, that loop
could be self-contradictory.
It might imply, for example,
that R was plugged into both X
and S on the plug board at once,
which is impossible.
The machine had no way to
catch this,
and every time the bomb stopped
and offered a solution,
an operator would have to check it.
So if there were 100 stops,
each of which might have taken
15 minutes to check,
that's more than 24 hours of work,
by which point
the Enigma settings
would have already changed.
The Bombe wasn't fast enough.
By the time
the first Bombe was operational,
the Nazis were already occupying
Austria and Czechoslovakia,
and they had invaded Poland,
killing hundreds of thousands
in the process.
Bletchley Park desperately
needed a way to speed up The Bombe.
Turing had managed expectations,
so it came as no great shock.
After that
a mathematician called Gordon
Welchman comes into the story.
Welchman, another Cambridge
mathematician, comes
to Bletchley Park,
working alongside Turing,
and he comes up
with a brilliant modification.
Welchman realized that guessing
R is plugged to
Y is exactly the same as guessing
that Y is plugged to R, so
Welchman connected these two wires
such that if one went live,
they both would.
He would do the same for S
and Y and R and S,
and this made it more likely
that a guess at the plug
board would set multiple
wires live, so exactly the same
input to the machine would rule out
more potential plug board swaps,
and therefore drastically reduce
the number of false positives.
Instead of the machine
stopping and giving you 100
possible solutions to check out,
you only get four.
Which means that process
was so much slicker.
So welchman's improvement
made the thing practical.
Welchman's modification
became known as the diagonal board,
and Turing figured out
that in many cases,
the diagonal board could eliminate
over 90% of false stops.
This new
version of The Bombe was ready
in August 1940,
but by now France had fallen
along with Norway and Denmark.
Britain was the last major power
in Western Europe, and the Nazis
had begun an aerial onslaught
trying to bring Britain
to its knees.
We shall defend our island,
whatever the cost.
We shall fight on beaches.
Hitler knows
if we can stand up to him
all Europe may be freed.
During the Battle of Britain,
when the question whether to commit
the last reserve
squadrons of fighters to the air
battle over over Britain,
the Air Force commander
felt able to do that
because the Enigma intelligence
had reinforced his own perceptions
about the balance of forces.
And we all know that
the outcome of that battle
was a victory for the British
and a strategic defeat
for the Germans.
By the end of 1941,
the British had 16 Bombes
in operation, six at Bletchley
and ten in the nearby towns,
and they were routinely deciphering
German Army and Luftwaffe
Enigma traffic.
This intelligence would soon help
turn the tide of the war
in North Africa.
Enigma decrypts
reveal that the German army
was critically short
of fuel and supplies.
Armed with that knowledge,
British General
Bernard Montgomery launched
the offensive
that culminated in the victory
at the Second Battle of
El Alamein in 1942.
What Turing did
was so resilient
to protocol changes
that it would have worked
at any time prior to this.
It is fundamental to the structure
of the Enigma machine,
and it's so fundamental
that they actually
ultimately
had to change the machine itself
in order to try to avoid this,
just to make it
like marginally more difficult
for them to to continue doing
by adding a fourth rotor.
And then even doing
that was a nightmare for them,
because you have to have it
be back or it's compatible.
So it's like
they kind of once Turing did that,
it was like, game over.
You either
reinvent the entire machine or,
you know, prevent them from knowing
any information whatsoever.
The German Navy did just that.
They added a fourth rotor
to the Naval Enigma machine,
and they created three extra rotors
to choose from.
Because of that, Turing
had to invent
a whole new statistical method
to narrow
down the choice of rotors,
and they also had to work
with the Navy to capture key
sheets and trick the Germans
into revealing a crib.
And they had to call
in the military
to try to generate plaintext
for them with gardening.
Well, sometimes if they were really
struggling to get plaintext, like
in the case of the blackout
with the Naval Enigma,
they would basically tell them
to seed mines
in particular locations,
and then those places would have
to go and clear them out.
And so they would
have to say the location.
- Oh that’s genius!
Yeah.
Oh, that's really cool.
But even then, the codebreakers
relied on the members of the British Navy
sacrificing their lives
to capture vital intelligence
from sinking U-boats.
I am conscious all the time
that codebreaking is not the same
as combat, and battles are not won
by codebreakers
sitting in rooms
in the safety of Bletchley Park.
They're won by people at the sharp
end of things.
By 1943,
the Americans had joined the war
and built
over 100 Bombes of their own.
You can see the turning point
of the war being when the British
finally mastered the U-boat Enigma
in 1943,
the sinkings drop like a stone,
and instead
the U-boat sinkings start to rise.
And that's that's the point
at which Germany has begun
to lose the war.
I'm not trying to say that Germany
lost the war solely because of the,
U-boat thing.
I mean, obviously the Eastern Front
was crucially important too
but all these things conspired
to mean that basically,
by the end of 1943,
everybody apart from Adolf
Hitler knew that the Germans
were going to lose.
Enigma traffic from all Nazi forces
was now being deciphered daily.
This set the stage
for the D-Day landings in 1944
and the Allied invasion of Europe.
Historians estimate that
the breaking of Enigma shortened
the war by up to two years, and
who knows how many lives had saved.
Alan Turing's life story
is dominated by his sexuality
and what happened to him.
Bearing in mind
that being a practicing homosexual
in the UK was still illegal
for the whole of Alan Turing's lifetime.
That story is very strongly colored
by the fact that Alan Turing
took his own life.
That tends to lead to a chain
of connections in people's minds,
that that means that his whole life
after World War
II was on a downward spiral.
I have to say, I disagree.
From 1945
through to 1950,
he was involved in the most
exciting technology projects
that the country had on offer.
He was very frustrated
from time to time
because they weren't going fast
enough.
You know, he was writing programs
for computers
that weren't yet being built.
So I think he achieved a great deal
in the postwar years.
And I have to say,
I think that the end of his life
does not actually define
what happened before.
And I think that we're
looking at it the wrong way.
If we see him
as some sort of martyr.
In 1944, Allied forces
were preparing to invade Europe.
But before they did,
Churchill and Roosevelt
launched one of the most important
misinformation
campaigns in history.
They leaked information
to the Nazis
that they were going to land
on a different beach.
The deception plan
about where the invasion of Europe
was going to take place,
was it going to be in Normandy
or was it going to be
at the Pas-de-Calais?
But before
the allies could land at Normandy,
they needed to know
whether this misinformation
campaign had actually worked.
And that meant deciphering messages
from Hitler himself.
Now that the enigma
had been broken.
That should have been easy.
But Hitler
actually didn't use Enigma.
He used a completely different
encryption machine, one
that the allies had never seen.
And while Enigma had a key space
of around ten to the power of 23,
this machine had a key
space of ten to the power of 170.
That's greater
than the number of atoms
in the observable universe squared.
To break
this would require
a piece of genius
that had been described
as the greatest
intellectual feat of World
War Two, and the building
of an entirely new machine vastly
more sophisticated than the Bombe.
Yet you've probably never heard
of the guy
who built it, or the codebreakers
who made it possible.
That's because this device
was so important
during the Cold War
that it was classified for decades
after the bomb and the Enigma.
If you want to hear about it.
Let us know in the comments.
Hey, I just want to give a quick
shout out to Bletchley Park,
the National Museum of Computing
and Sir Dermot Turing
and every expert here
who has helped us
make this video possible.
If you're interested in visiting,
all the links
are in the description,
so check that out.
One last thing, by the way, there's
still a Naval Enigma message
intercepted in the war that no one
has been able to decrypt.
The ciphertext
is in the description.
Maybe you can break
it. Let us know if you can.